Guide to the Records of the Office of the Assistant to the Chancellor/President (James W. Armsey) RG.3.1.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Assistant to the Chancellor/President (James W. Armsey)
1951-1957
New York University Archives
Armsey, James W., 1917-2008
RG.3.1.1
3.5 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes
This collection is comprised of the papers of James W. Armsey, who worked as the Assistant to the Chancellor, Henry T. Heald, at New York University (NYU) for four years starting in 1952. It is made up of clippings, personal letters, and public relations documents.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Biographical Note
James William Armsey was born December 13, 1917, and he received his B.S. at the University of Illinois in 1941 and his M.A. in 1946. After graduation, Armsey worked in the Public Information Office of the University of Illinois Professional Colleges. After a year at this post, Armsey went on to serve five years as the Public Relations Director at the Illinois Institute of Technology. This experience prepared him to serve as Assistant to the Chancellor at New York University (NYU) beginning in 1952. During his four years at NYU, Armsey would hold several positions. Besides being Assistant to the Chancellor, Armsey was also the head of Public Relations, and the Vice President and Director of the New York University Press. He was an administrator for the Challenge newspaper and had ties to the Alumni Bulletin, Alumni News, and the NYU Daily Bulletin. Armsey was also a member of the Community Planning Board #2, helping to clean up the Washington Square area and acquire sites for buildings to expand the Washington Square campus. During Armsey's time at NYU, Henry T. Heald was Chancellor. Heald had been President of the Illinois Institute of Technology, and when he was appointed Chancellor of NYU, he brought Armsey to New York with him as his assistant. When Heald became president of the Ford Foundation, Armsey joined him there.
Sources Hevesi, Dennis. "James Armsey Dies at 90, Oversaw College Grants", The New York Times, November 19, 2008
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of personal letters, correspondence, press releases, newspaper articles, pamphlets, transcripts, and meeting minutes relating to New York University from 1952-1956. The papers contain information on the gift of the land estate of Frank Jay Gould, the dedication of the Gould Student Center, and the NYU-Bellevue Medical Center. There are a number of files on various aspects of fundraising, the expansion of the NYU Press, public broadcasting, and plans to make a film history of NYU. This collection also contains materials pertaining to Edwin Berry Burgum. Burgum, a tenured faculty member in the Department of English, was subpoenaed by the Senate Internal Sub-Committee on the Judiciary in October 1952 and was dismissed by Chancellor Heald after his appearance and refusal to testify. Burgum protested and requested a review, and as a result, a lengthy hearing was held by the faculty membership of the University Senate. On April 15, 1953, it recommended that Burgum's dismissal be sustained. The files on Burgum include news clippings, the transcript of the Senate Sub-Committee hearings, news releases, excerpts from the minutes of an October 1952 NYU Council meeting, and replies to letters on Burgum's suspension.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Office of Public Relations.
Scholarships.; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; Radio broadcasting -- History; Universities and Colleges -- Alumni and alumnae.; Newsom, Carroll V. (Carroll Vincent), 1904-1990; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance.; Gould Memorial Library; New York University; Gould, Frank Jay; Bellevue Hospital Medical College; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townly), 1904-1975; NYU Press; Burgum, Edwin Berry, 1894-
- Administrative Staff Meetings, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Administrative Staff Meetings, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Air Force ROTC, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Alumni Affairs, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Alumni Bulletin and News, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Council on Education, 1952, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ankara, University of, & NYU, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 125th Anniversary Celebration, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Armstrong, George Ellis, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Arts Center, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Arts and Science, Graduate School, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Aspen, Colorado, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Assemblies, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Athletic Policy, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Athletics, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Atomic Energy Commission, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Awards, citations, etc., 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Building and Centers, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Burgum, Edwin Berry, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Burgum, Edwin Berry II, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Business Administration Graduate School, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Challenge, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chase, Harry Woodburn, death, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Christian Association, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Christian Association, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Civil Defense, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Commencement, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Commerce, School of, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- RESTRICTED - Communication Arts Group, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Community Relations, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Conferences at NYU, 1953, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Daily Bulletin, NYU, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Education, School of, 1953, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Engineering, College of, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Enrollment, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Film on NYU, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Financial History of NYU, 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Fine Arts, Institute of, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Fraternities & Sororities, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Gallatin, Albert, Associates., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- General Education, Division of, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Gifts and Grants, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Glee Club, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Gould, Frank Jay, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Gould Student Center, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Hall of Fame, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Heald, Henry T., 1953, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Henry, David D., 1951-1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- History of NYU, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Howley, Frank L., 1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Industry - College Conference, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Industry - College Conference II, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- International School (UNESCO), 1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Information Services, Office., 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Kimball, Leroy E., 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Libraries, 1937-1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Loeb Student Center, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Mathematical Science, Institute of, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Medical Center, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- META I, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- META II, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Morse, Samuel F.B., 1954 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Newsom, Carrol V., 1955-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- New York Times, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- New York University, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- News Releases, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Photographers, Office of, 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Placement Services, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Public Administration, Graduate School of, 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Public Occasions, Bureau of, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Public Relations, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Public Relations II, 1954-1956 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Public Relations III, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Public Relations, Courses on, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Publications and Printing Office, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Publications Review Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Radio and Television Office, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Radio and Television Office, 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Radio - Television Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Recruitment Office, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Religious Center and Activities, 1948-1956 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Research Services, Office Of, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Retailing, School of, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Scholarship Committee, 1930-1952 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Scholarship Committee II, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Scholarship Committee III, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Scholarship Committee IV, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Self Study, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Smith, Rufus D., 1952 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Stokes Lectures, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Student Matters and Activities, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Student Newspapers, 1953-1955 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Summer Session, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Television, 1952-1956 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Television Closed Circuit, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- TV - Ed. Tv and Radio Center, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Television "Yesterday's W.", 1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Tuition, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- University Development, Office Of, 1952-1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- University Press, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- University Press, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- University Press, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- University Press Advisory Board, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- University Press Editorial Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Voorhis, Harold O., 1951-1954 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Washington Square College, 1953-1956 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Washington Square, Site Maps, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Glass plate negatives: J.W. Armsey, Feb. 28, 1978; Personalities, Administrative charts; Campus views of Heald Administration, circa 1950s (Box Shared University Archives 020)